<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Learning on Pavan Chavali</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/tags/learning/</link><description>Recent content in Learning on Pavan Chavali</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pchavali09.github.io/tags/learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Episode 1: From APIs to AI MCP — The Next Chapter of Enterprise Integrations</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/episode1-apis-ai-mcp/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/episode1-apis-ai-mcp/</guid><description>
&lt;img src="https://pchavali09.github.io/1WEsmOlXSG8A13qWPieHztQ.jpeg" alt="Cover Image" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever spent late nights debugging APIs, juggling integration flows, or wondering why your “connected systems” don’t actually &lt;em&gt;talk&lt;/em&gt; to each other — this one’s for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This 4-part series explores how enterprise integrations are evolving from traditional APIs and middleware to something smarter — &lt;strong&gt;AI MCP (Model Context Protocol)&lt;/strong&gt; — a new way for systems to communicate &lt;em&gt;intelligently&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(In this first episode, we’ll explore what MCP is, why it matters, and how it changes the way we think about integration.)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Unveiling the Power of Salesforce Experience Cloud in Digital Transformation</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/unveiling-the-power-of-salesforce-experience-cloud-in-digital-transformation-43a2c0abd91b/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/unveiling-the-power-of-salesforce-experience-cloud-in-digital-transformation-43a2c0abd91b/</guid><description>
&lt;h3 id="overview"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the ever-evolving landscape of customer engagement, Salesforce Experience Cloud emerges as a pivotal player, reshaping the way organizations connect with their audiences. Formerly known as Community Cloud, Experience Cloud serves as a robust platform for constructing tailored digital experiences seamlessly integrated with CRM functionalities. Within the Salesforce ecosystem, Experience Cloud facilitates customer self-service and empowers partners through Partner Relationship Management (PRM) capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experience Cloud, essentially, empowers businesses to craft bespoke digital interfaces leveraging standard Salesforce development tools. Its key features include:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>