<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Salesforce-Development on Pavan Chavali</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/tags/salesforce-development/</link><description>Recent content in Salesforce-Development on Pavan Chavali</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pchavali09.github.io/tags/salesforce-development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Using the "Changes Since" Filter for Better Salesforce Pipeline Inspection</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/salesforce-pipeline-episode-2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/salesforce-pipeline-episode-2/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ever found yourself staring at your Salesforce Pipeline Inspection dashboard, scratching your head? You know a deal moved, but it’s not showing up where you expect it to. Or perhaps it appears under “This Week” but vanishes when you select “2 Weeks Ago”?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that sounds familiar, you’re not alone. Pipeline Inspection is a powerful tool for sales leaders and reps, offering dynamic insights into pipeline health. But its “Changes Since” filter, particularly how it calculates “Moved In” and “Moved Out” opportunities, can sometimes feel like a magic trick. Today, we’re pulling back the curtain on that magic, using a real-world scenario to explain exactly what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Guide to Using Salesforce Flows for Cross Object Validation</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/salesforce-flows-automation/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/salesforce-flows-automation/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://pchavali09.github.io/06i69eJ2WQkRv7TWv.jpg" alt="Guide to Using Salesforce Flows for Cross Object Validation" style="max-width: 100%; margin-bottom: 20px;" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Salesforce consistently enhances Flows with each release, transforming them into a more robust and user-friendly feature. These improvements simplify usage and effectively address complex requirements that cannot be met through declarative means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you know you can now implement cross-object validation rules without writing Apex code?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until now, if you needed to check related records, like verifying their existence or displaying error messages to prevent record deletion in specific scenarios, or developers had to rely on Apex code.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>