<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Developer on Pavan's Blog</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/tags/developer/</link><description>Recent content in Developer on Pavan's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.152.2</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pchavali09.github.io/tags/developer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Platform Renaissance: Why the Future of Enterprise SaaS Is Composable</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/the-platform-renaissance-why-the-future-of-enterprise-saas-is-composable/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/the-platform-renaissance-why-the-future-of-enterprise-saas-is-composable/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;For nearly two decades, the enterprise IT playbook has been clear and consistent. In the “Build vs. Buy” debate, the answer overwhelmingly leaned toward &lt;strong&gt;Buy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We adopted Salesforce, Workday, ServiceNow, and other SaaS platforms because they were secure, scalable, and significantly cheaper and faster than building enterprise systems from scratch. The costs, maintenance, and complexity of custom systems made SaaS the pragmatic choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a shift is underway. Enterprises are beginning to ask a deeper question:&lt;/p&gt;</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For nearly two decades, the enterprise IT playbook has been clear and consistent. In the “Build vs. Buy” debate, the answer overwhelmingly leaned toward <strong>Buy</strong>.</p>
<p>We adopted Salesforce, Workday, ServiceNow, and other SaaS platforms because they were secure, scalable, and significantly cheaper and faster than building enterprise systems from scratch. The costs, maintenance, and complexity of custom systems made SaaS the pragmatic choice.</p>
<p>But a shift is underway. Enterprises are beginning to ask a deeper question:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>What if the real power isn’t in the cloud you buy — but in the platform beneath it?</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="why-now">Why Now</h3>
<p>This shift is being driven by two major industry-wide transformations:</p>
<h3 id="1-the-maturing-of-in-housetalent">1. The Maturing of In-House Talent</h3>
<p>Ten years ago, large engineering teams were mostly found in tech companies.<br>
Today — banks, retailers, manufacturers, insurers, logistics companies — <strong>every enterprise is a technology company</strong>.</p>
<p>This is fueling the <strong>Platform Engineering megatrend</strong>.</p>
<p>Gartner predicts that by <strong>2026</strong>,</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>80% of large software engineering organizations will establish platform engineering teams.</strong>(<a href="https://www.gartner.com/en/newsroom/press-releases/2023-11-28-gartner-hype-cycle-shows-ai-practices-and-platform-engineering-will-reach-mainstream-adoption-in-software-engineering-in-two-to-five-years">Gartner — Top Strategic Technology Trends</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>These teams build <strong>Internal Developer Platforms (IDPs)</strong> to standardize how enterprise engineers build systems internally. They’re no longer simple “software consumers” — they’re sophisticated builders.</p>
<p>Gartner has also continued to advocate for <strong>composable architecture</strong>, aligned to modularity, speed, and reuse.</p>
<p>And another key data point:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>By 2027, 50% of enterprise software engineers will use ML-powered coding tools.</strong> (<a href="https://www.gartner.com/en/newsroom/press-releases/2023-11-28-gartner-hype-cycle-shows-ai-practices-and-platform-engineering-will-reach-mainstream-adoption-in-software-engineering-in-two-to-five-years">Gartner — Software Engineering Trends</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="2-the-rise-of-ai-as-a-developer">2. The Rise of AI as a Developer</h3>
<p>Generative AI is completely reshaping the economics of software development.</p>
<p><strong>AI now:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Writes large portions of production-grade code</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Builds tests</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Generates documentation</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Improves code quality</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Reduces long-term maintenance overhead</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>The old barriers that made “Build” expensive are eroding quickly.</p>
<p>AI means that building is no longer a high-cost, long-term liability — it’s becoming a <strong>strategic advantage</strong>, especially when the solution differentiates your business.</p>
<h3 id="not-just-a-return-to-build-vsbuy">Not Just a Return to “Build vs. Buy”</h3>
<p>Some frame this shift as reopening the old debate. But this is bigger. This is not “Build” versus “Buy.” This is a <strong>new model</strong>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Buy the Platform. Build the Differentiation.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>We are entering the <strong>Platform Renaissance</strong>, aligned with what Gartner calls the <strong>Composable Enterprise</strong> — a world where organizations assemble capabilities like Lego blocks.</p>
<h3 id="the-ai-powered-platform-first-opportunity">The AI-Powered Platform-First Opportunity</h3>
<p>The future of enterprise IT isn’t in vertical SaaS apps. It’s in platforms that empower organizations to build what truly differentiates them. SaaS vendors can evolve by offering:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Horizontal Capabilities: Workflow engines, Analytics, AI automation</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Extensible building blocks: data models, UI templates, SDKs</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Open composition: customers assemble apps themselves</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Instead of selling <strong>Service Cloud v3</strong>, vendors could provide: A secure, metadata-driven, AI-native platform where enterprise engineers and citizen developers build their own solutions — fast. This enables enterprises to:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Maintain innovation speed</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Avoid vendor lock-in</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Reduce expensive custom rebuilds</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Use vendor strengths while building unique IP</p>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://www.gartner.com/en/newsroom/press-releases/2025-10-20-gartner-identifies-the-top-strategic-technology-trends-for-2026">Gartner — Top Strategic Technology Trends for 2026: Composable Platforms &amp; AI-Native Development</a></p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="the-new-opportunity-unbundle-dontreplace">The New Opportunity: Unbundle, Don’t Replace</h3>
<p>This shift isn’t about discarding existing systems.</p>
<p>It’s about <strong>unbundling them</strong>.</p>
<p>A very telling example: A recent job posting for a <em>Salesforce Developer (AI/Einstein)</em> didn’t simply ask for app admin skills. It asked for the ability to:</p>
<p><em>“Design, build, and productionize Salesforce-native AI features and Build on-platform AI capabilities”</em></p>
<p>That job description reflects what enterprises actually want from SaaS vendors today —</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Give us your governance, security, reliability, and world-class AI stack.<br>
And give us the freedom to build the last-mile differentiation ourselves.</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>SaaS vendors that pivot from “product providers” to <strong>platform enablers</strong> will define the next decade of enterprise software.</p>
<p>They will become the <strong>foundation layer</strong> for AI-driven, customizable enterprise applications.</p>
<h3 id="vendors-best-positioned-tolead">Vendors Best Positioned to Lead</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Salesforce:</strong> Already progressing toward a metadata-first, AI-native extensible platform.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Microsoft:</strong> Power Platform + Azure offer some of the strongest building-block primitives in the market.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>ServiceNow:</strong> Now Platform increasingly resembles a modular business OS.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Oracle:</strong> Fusion Cloud + Oracle’s developer tooling make it a strong contender for platform-driven enterprise architectures.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>“The future of enterprise IT isn’t just what you buy.<br>
It’s what you can build on top of it.”</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The next decade of enterprise software won’t be defined by the tools we buy, but by the platforms we build upon.</p>
<p>The real question for CIOs, architects, and product leaders now is simple:<br>
<em><strong>Will your organization be a consumer of SaaS — or a creator of strategic advantage?</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Note: This article was written by the author with editing assistance from AI &amp; Illustrations generated with the help of AI</em></p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Using the "Changes Since" Filter for Better Salesforce Pipeline Inspection</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/changes-since-filter-salesforce-pipeline-inspection/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/changes-since-filter-salesforce-pipeline-inspection/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ever found yourself staring at your Salesforce Pipeline Inspection dashboard, scratching your head? You know a deal moved, but it’s not showing up where you expect it to. Or perhaps it appears under “This Week” but vanishes when you select “2 Weeks Ago”?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that sounds familiar, you’re not alone. Pipeline Inspection is a powerful tool for sales leaders and reps, offering dynamic insights into pipeline health. But its “Changes Since” filter, particularly how it calculates “Moved In” and “Moved Out” opportunities, can sometimes feel like a magic trick. Today, we’re pulling back the curtain on that magic, using a real-world scenario to explain exactly what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ever found yourself staring at your Salesforce Pipeline Inspection dashboard, scratching your head? You know a deal moved, but it’s not showing up where you expect it to. Or perhaps it appears under “This Week” but vanishes when you select “2 Weeks Ago”?</p>
<p>If that sounds familiar, you’re not alone. Pipeline Inspection is a powerful tool for sales leaders and reps, offering dynamic insights into pipeline health. But its “Changes Since” filter, particularly how it calculates “Moved In” and “Moved Out” opportunities, can sometimes feel like a magic trick. Today, we’re pulling back the curtain on that magic, using a real-world scenario to explain exactly what’s going on.</p>
<h3 id="first-a-quick-recap-the-coreconcepts">First, A Quick Recap: The Core Concepts</h3>
<p>Before we dive into the puzzle, let’s ensure we’re on the same page with two fundamental Salesforce concepts:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Close Date:</strong> This is the anticipated (for open deals) or actual (for closed deals) date by which an opportunity is expected to be won or lost. It’s the heartbeat of your sales forecast.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Pipeline Inspection’s “Changes Since” Filter:</strong> This ingenious filter shows you how your opportunities have evolved from a specific point in time up to the present. It tracks changes to amounts, stages, forecast categories, and critically for our discussion: opportunities that have “Moved In” or “Moved Out” of your chosen forecast period.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="the-curious-case-of-the-elusive-opportunity">The Curious Case of the Elusive Opportunity</h3>
<p>Let’s set the stage with a very specific example, straight from a recent conversation:</p>
<p>Imagine it’s <strong>Sunday, June 15, 2025</strong>. You’re viewing your Pipeline Inspection dashboard, focused on the <strong>“This Quarter” (Q2: April 1 — June 30, 2025)</strong> forecast period.</p>
<p>You have an Opportunity with this history:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Original Close Date:</strong> July 4, 2025 (initially in Q3)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Change 1:</strong> On <strong>June 4, 2025</strong>, you moved its Close Date from July 4, 2025 <strong>to June 30, 2025</strong>. <em>(This moved the opportunity INTO “This Quarter”)</em></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Change 2:</strong> On <strong>June 9, 2025</strong>, you moved its Close Date from June 30, 2025 <strong>to August 30, 2025</strong>. <em>(This moved the opportunity OUT of “This Quarter”)</em></p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Now for the baffling part: You observe that this opportunity <strong>shows up as “Moved Out” when you select ‘Changes Since: This Week’</strong>, but it <strong>does NOT show up when you select ‘Changes Since: 2 Weeks Ago’</strong>.</p>
<p>Why the inconsistency? Let’s unpack it.</p>
<h3 id="dissecting-the-filters-the-starting-point-is-everything">Dissecting the Filters: The “Starting Point” is Everything</h3>
<p>The key to understanding this lies in how Pipeline Inspection defines the <em>start</em> of each “Changes Since” window, and how it uses that starting point to determine “Moved In” or “Moved Out” status relative to your <strong>selected forecast period</strong>.</p>
<h4 id="filter-1-changes-since-thisweek">Filter 1: ‘Changes Since: This Week’</h4>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>What it means:</strong> All changes that happened since the very beginning of the current calendar week.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Our Start Time (for Sunday, June 15):</strong> Monday, June 9, 2025, 12:00:00 AM EDT.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>**Analysis:<br>
**– <strong>At the start of this filter (June 9, 12 AM EDT):</strong> Our opportunity’s Close Date was <strong>June 30, 2025</strong>. This date falls <strong>inside</strong> “This Quarter” (April 1 — June 30).<br>
– <strong>During this filter’s window (on June 9):</strong> The Close Date was changed from June 30, 2025, to August 30, 2025. This new date falls <strong>outside</strong> “This Quarter”.<br>
– <strong>Result:</strong> The opportunity was <em>inside</em> “This Quarter” at the start of ‘This Week’ and then moved <em>outside</em> “This Quarter” during ‘This Week’. This perfectly fits the “Moved Out” criteria.<br>
– <strong>Verdict:</strong> <strong>It WILL show up as “Moved Out” in ‘This Week’. (Matches your observation!)</strong></p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="filter-2-changes-since-2-weeksago">Filter 2: ‘Changes Since: 2 Weeks Ago’</h4>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>What it means:</strong> All changes that happened since exactly two weeks prior to the current moment.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Our Start Time (for Sunday, June 15, 5:53:15 PM EDT):</strong> Sunday, June 1, 2025, 5:53:15 PM EDT.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>**Analysis:<br>
**– <strong>At the start of this filter (June 1, 5:53:15 PM EDT):</strong> Our opportunity’s Close Date was <strong>July 4, 2025</strong> (because the change to June 30 hadn’t happened yet, as it occurred on June 4).<br>
– Is July 4, 2025 <strong>within</strong> “This Quarter” (April 1 — June 30)? <strong>NO.</strong> (It’s in Q3).<br>
– <strong>Result:</strong> For an opportunity to be “Moved Out” by this filter, it needed to be <em>inside</em> “This Quarter” on June 1. Since it was <em>already outside</em> “This Quarter” at that starting point, it cannot be counted as having “moved out” <em>from that specific perspective</em>. Even though it moved in and then out <em>within</em> the 2-week window, its starting status for this particular filter disqualifies it from the “Moved Out” category.<br>
– <strong>Verdict:</strong> <strong>It will NOT show up as “Moved Out” in ‘2 Weeks Ago’. (Matches your observation!)</strong></p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="the-takeaway-its-all-about-thebaseline">The Takeaway: It’s All About the Baseline</h3>
<p>The critical lesson here is that Salesforce Pipeline Inspection’s “Moved In” and “Moved Out” metrics are calculated by comparing the opportunity’s status <strong>at the exact beginning of your chosen ‘Changes Since’ filter</strong> to its current status, all relative to your <strong>selected Forecast Period</strong>.</p>
<p>It’s not just about when a change happened, but what the opportunity’s state was <em>at the baseline of the comparison</em>. This allows sales managers to accurately understand pipeline dynamics from different historical vantage points.</p>
<p>So, the next time you’re reviewing your pipeline, remember the power of that “Changes Since” filter and how its starting point dictates the story it tells.</p>
<h3 id="what-are-your-pipeline-mysteries">What are your pipeline mysteries?</h3>
<p>Have you encountered similar head-scratching moments in Salesforce Pipeline Inspection? Or perhaps you have other filters or metrics you’d like us to demystify? Share your thoughts, questions, and experiences in the comments below! Let’s build a clearer understanding of our sales data together.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>