<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Architecture on Pavan Chavali</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/tags/architecture/</link><description>Recent content in Architecture on Pavan Chavali</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pchavali09.github.io/tags/architecture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The AI Mirage: Why LLMs Flunk the Salesforce Exam (And How We Fix It)</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/llms-flunks-salesforce/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/llms-flunks-salesforce/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/llms-flunks-salesforce/futuristic-ai-robot.png" alt="The AI Mirage: Why LLMs Flunk the Salesforce Exam (And How We Fix It)" style="max-width: 100%; margin-bottom: 20px;" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Everyone is telling us that the Fourth Industrial Revolution is here. The promise is seductive: AI copilots that know everything, code everything, and debug everything. For a Salesforce Architect like me—someone who spends their days architecting secure, scalable systems at the enterprise level—the pitch is that I can finally offload the boilerplate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the reality? It’s&amp;hellip; jagged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether I’m using ChatGPT, Gemini, MS Copilot, or early versions of Agentforce, I keep hitting a wall. It’s not just that the AI doesn’t know things; it’s that it &lt;em&gt;hallucinates&lt;/em&gt; them with total confidence. It invents features that don’t exist and writes code that looks perfect but crashes instantly.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Architecting Freedom: Building a Secure, Serverless Portfolio for $0</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/architecting-freedom/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/architecting-freedom/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/architecting-freedom/posts/architecting-freedom/architecting-freedom-cover.png" alt="Architecting Freedom: Building a Secure, Serverless Portfolio for $0" style="max-width: 100%; margin-bottom: 20px;" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I architect systems for a living. I spend my days designing secure, scalable ecosystems for Fortune 500 companies, ensuring data flows correctly between Salesforce, Mulesoft, and AI agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, for the longest time, my own digital home was built on &amp;ldquo;rented land.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was writing on platforms like Hashnode and Medium. They are fantastic tools, but they are &lt;strong&gt;Black Boxes&lt;/strong&gt;. I found myself wrestling with random timeouts, Cloudflare verification loops, limited free articles that blocked my readers, and rigid styling that felt like wearing a uniform.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Episode 2: MCP vs MuleSoft: Friends, Not Foes</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/episode-2-mcp-vs-mulesoft/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/episode-2-mcp-vs-mulesoft/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/episode-2-mcp-vs-mulesoft/1HAaxry-sRt6_ahsalOB3BQ.png" alt="Episode 2: MCP vs MuleSoft: Friends, Not Foes" style="max-width: 100%; margin-bottom: 20px;" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’ve read Episode 1, you probably remember how we opened the door to this new world of &lt;strong&gt;AI MCP (Model Context Protocol)&lt;/strong&gt; — the idea that systems could start reasoning, not just integrating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It felt exciting, futuristic… maybe &lt;em&gt;too good to be true&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
And honestly, that’s what I’ve been thinking about ever since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because like most of you who’ve lived through long integration nights, broken APIs, and “mysterious” data mismatches — I’ve learned that &lt;em&gt;every shiny new thing&lt;/em&gt; comes with its own set of “gotchas.”&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>