<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Automation on Pavan Chavali</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/tags/automation/</link><description>Recent content in Automation on Pavan Chavali</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pchavali09.github.io/tags/automation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Episode 4: The "iBrain" Era — When Integration Stops Being a To-Do List</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/episode-4-ibrain-era/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/episode-4-ibrain-era/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/episode-4-ibrain-era/ipaas-to-ibrain.webp" alt="Episode 4: The "iBrain" Era — When Integration Stops Being a To-Do List" style="max-width: 100%; margin-bottom: 20px;" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’ve been on quite a journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;Episode 1&lt;/strong&gt;, we learned that MCP is the new nervous system for AI. In &lt;strong&gt;Episode 2&lt;/strong&gt;, we made peace with MuleSoft (integration’s heavy lifter). In &lt;strong&gt;Episode 3&lt;/strong&gt;, we stood at the fork in the road and chose our protocol—Open Source or Enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, we turn the key. We stop looking at architecture diagrams and start looking at &lt;em&gt;behaviour&lt;/em&gt;. Because when you actually switch this on, something fundamental shifts.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Episode 2: MCP vs MuleSoft: Friends, Not Foes</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/episode-2-mcp-vs-mulesoft/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/episode-2-mcp-vs-mulesoft/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/episode-2-mcp-vs-mulesoft/1HAaxry-sRt6_ahsalOB3BQ.webp" alt="Episode 2: MCP vs MuleSoft: Friends, Not Foes" style="max-width: 100%; margin-bottom: 20px;" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’ve read Episode 1, you probably remember how we opened the door to this new world of &lt;strong&gt;AI MCP (Model Context Protocol)&lt;/strong&gt; — the idea that systems could start reasoning, not just integrating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It felt exciting, futuristic… maybe &lt;em&gt;too good to be true&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
And honestly, that’s what I’ve been thinking about ever since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because like most of you who’ve lived through long integration nights, broken APIs, and “mysterious” data mismatches — I’ve learned that &lt;em&gt;every shiny new thing&lt;/em&gt; comes with its own set of “gotchas.”&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>I Built an AI “Copilot” to Automate My Most Annoying Task: Logging Emails in Salesforce</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/email-automation/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/email-automation/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/email-automation/email-copilot-automation.webp" alt="I Built an AI “Copilot” to Automate My Most Annoying Task: Logging Emails in Salesforce" style="max-width: 100%; margin-bottom: 20px;" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h3 id="how-a-custom-outlook-add-in-azure-functions-and-ai-can-eliminate-manual-data-entry-and-create-perfect-crm-notes-or-tasks-everytime"&gt;How a custom Outlook Add-in, Azure Functions, and AI can eliminate manual data entry and create perfect CRM notes or tasks every time.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every professional who uses a CRM has felt this pain. You finish an important email exchange with a client — full of critical details, action items, and subtle sentiment cues — and then comes the administrative tax: logging it all in Salesforce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You copy and paste, you try to summarize the key points, you search for the right Account or Opportunity, and you create a Task. It’s a tedious, time-consuming process that’s universally disliked yet essential for maintaining a clear customer record.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Mastering Salesforce Pipeline: Effective Use of Preset &amp; Side Panel Filters</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/salesforce-pipeline-episode-1/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/salesforce-pipeline-episode-1/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ever found yourself in Salesforce Pipeline Inspection, meticulously applying filters at the top of the page, only to open the “Show Filters” panel on the right (that handy three-lines icon) and see it unchanged? It’s a common point of confusion: why don’t these filter sections seem to “talk” to each other?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve experienced this, you’re not alone. This behaviour isn’t a bug; it’s a deliberate design choice by Salesforce that, once understood, can unlock a more powerful and intuitive pipeline analysis experience. Let’s break down the distinct roles of these two filter areas and how to master their interaction.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Using the "Changes Since" Filter for Better Salesforce Pipeline Inspection</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/salesforce-pipeline-episode-2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/salesforce-pipeline-episode-2/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ever found yourself staring at your Salesforce Pipeline Inspection dashboard, scratching your head? You know a deal moved, but it’s not showing up where you expect it to. Or perhaps it appears under “This Week” but vanishes when you select “2 Weeks Ago”?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that sounds familiar, you’re not alone. Pipeline Inspection is a powerful tool for sales leaders and reps, offering dynamic insights into pipeline health. But its “Changes Since” filter, particularly how it calculates “Moved In” and “Moved Out” opportunities, can sometimes feel like a magic trick. Today, we’re pulling back the curtain on that magic, using a real-world scenario to explain exactly what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Improve Partner Collaboration Using Salesforce: Master User Automation</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/partner-collaboration/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/partner-collaboration/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/partner-collaboration/0ojd0rP-gNEkHrWTu.webp" alt="Improve Partner Collaboration Using Salesforce: Master User Automation" style="max-width: 100%; margin-bottom: 20px;" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h3 id="overview"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today’s fast-paced business world, working efficiently with partners is essential. Salesforce CPQ (Configure, Price, Quote) and Experience Cloud together can greatly improve the way partners interact with your business. This three-part series will show you how these tools can make partner interactions smoother and more productive. We’ll start by focusing on user automation in the first part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In “Mastering User Automation,” we’ll look at how automating user-related tasks can save time and reduce mistakes. Key features we’ll cover include setting up user accounts automatically, automating workflows, and sending customized notifications. These tools ensure partners get the right access at the right time, making things easier for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Guide to Using Salesforce Flows for Cross Object Validation</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/salesforce-flows-automation/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/salesforce-flows-automation/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/salesforce-flows-automation/06i69eJ2WQkRv7TWv.webp" alt="Guide to Using Salesforce Flows for Cross Object Validation" style="max-width: 100%; margin-bottom: 20px;" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Salesforce consistently enhances Flows with each release, transforming them into a more robust and user-friendly feature. These improvements simplify usage and effectively address complex requirements that cannot be met through declarative means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you know you can now implement cross-object validation rules without writing Apex code?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until now, if you needed to check related records, like verifying their existence or displaying error messages to prevent record deletion in specific scenarios, or developers had to rely on Apex code.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>