<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Artificial-Intelligence on Pavan Chavali</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/tags/artificial-intelligence/</link><description>Recent content in Artificial-Intelligence on Pavan Chavali</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pchavali09.github.io/tags/artificial-intelligence/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Episode 2: MCP vs MuleSoft: Friends, Not Foes</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/episode-2-mcp-vs-mulesoft/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/episode-2-mcp-vs-mulesoft/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://pchavali09.github.io/tags/artificial-intelligence/1HAaxry-sRt6_ahsalOB3BQ.png" alt="Episode 2: MCP vs MuleSoft: Friends, Not Foes" style="max-width: 100%; margin-bottom: 20px;" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’ve read Episode 1, you probably remember how we opened the door to this new world of &lt;strong&gt;AI MCP (Model Context Protocol)&lt;/strong&gt; — the idea that systems could start reasoning, not just integrating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It felt exciting, futuristic… maybe &lt;em&gt;too good to be true&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
And honestly, that’s what I’ve been thinking about ever since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because like most of you who’ve lived through long integration nights, broken APIs, and “mysterious” data mismatches — I’ve learned that &lt;em&gt;every shiny new thing&lt;/em&gt; comes with its own set of “gotchas.”&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Platform Renaissance: Why the Future of Enterprise SaaS Is Composable</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/platform-renaissance/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/platform-renaissance/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://pchavali09.github.io/tags/artificial-intelligence/19rA7cZugEHvJ-Bk0o17w8Q.png" alt="The Platform Renaissance: Why the Future of Enterprise SaaS Is Composable" style="max-width: 100%; margin-bottom: 20px;" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;For nearly two decades, the enterprise IT playbook has been clear and consistent. In the “Build vs. Buy” debate, the answer overwhelmingly leaned toward &lt;strong&gt;Buy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We adopted Salesforce, Workday, ServiceNow, and other SaaS platforms because they were secure, scalable, and significantly cheaper and faster than building enterprise systems from scratch. The costs, maintenance, and complexity of custom systems made SaaS the pragmatic choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a shift is underway. Enterprises are beginning to ask a deeper question:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Rise of the Agentic Enterprise: How Salesforce’s Agentforce 360 Is Changing Work Forever</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/agentic-enterprise/</link><pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/agentic-enterprise/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://pchavali09.github.io/tags/artificial-intelligence/2151422f-6653-4b45-aa63-3a6c716ff5bb.png" alt="The Rise of the Agentic Enterprise: How Salesforce’s Agentforce 360 Is Changing Work Forever" style="max-width: 100%; margin-bottom: 20px;" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Salesforce announced Agentforce in 2024, it felt like a glimpse into the future of AI in the enterprise. Fast forward to Dreamforce 2025, and that vision has evolved — now it’s about Agentforce 360 and something Salesforce calls the Agentic Enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Agentforce 360 connects AI agents, humans, data, and workflows to elevate human potential in the age of AI.”&lt;br&gt;
 —&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.salesforce.com/news/press-releases/2025/10/13/agentic-enterprise-announcement/?utm_source=chatgpt.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Salesforce Press Release, Dreamforce 2025&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first glance, it sounds like another big buzzword moment. But if you look closer, Salesforce is signalling something much deeper — a shift from “AI features” to AI teammates that work &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; us, not just &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; us.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>I Built an AI “Copilot” to Automate My Most Annoying Task: Logging Emails in Salesforce</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/email-automation/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/email-automation/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://pchavali09.github.io/tags/artificial-intelligence/email-copilot-automation.png" alt="I Built an AI “Copilot” to Automate My Most Annoying Task: Logging Emails in Salesforce" style="max-width: 100%; margin-bottom: 20px;" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h3 id="how-a-custom-outlook-add-in-azure-functions-and-ai-can-eliminate-manual-data-entry-and-create-perfect-crm-notes-or-tasks-everytime"&gt;How a custom Outlook Add-in, Azure Functions, and AI can eliminate manual data entry and create perfect CRM notes or tasks every time.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every professional who uses a CRM has felt this pain. You finish an important email exchange with a client — full of critical details, action items, and subtle sentiment cues — and then comes the administrative tax: logging it all in Salesforce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You copy and paste, you try to summarize the key points, you search for the right Account or Opportunity, and you create a Task. It’s a tedious, time-consuming process that’s universally disliked yet essential for maintaining a clear customer record.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>