<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>[Mastering Salesforce Pipeline Inspector] on Pavan Chavali</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/series/mastering-salesforce-pipeline-inspector/</link><description>Recent content in [Mastering Salesforce Pipeline Inspector] on Pavan Chavali</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pchavali09.github.io/series/mastering-salesforce-pipeline-inspector/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Mastering Salesforce Pipeline: Effective Use of Preset &amp; Side Panel Filters</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/salesforce-pipeline-episode-1/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/salesforce-pipeline-episode-1/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ever found yourself in Salesforce Pipeline Inspection, meticulously applying filters at the top of the page, only to open the “Show Filters” panel on the right (that handy three-lines icon) and see it unchanged? It’s a common point of confusion: why don’t these filter sections seem to “talk” to each other?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve experienced this, you’re not alone. This behaviour isn’t a bug; it’s a deliberate design choice by Salesforce that, once understood, can unlock a more powerful and intuitive pipeline analysis experience. Let’s break down the distinct roles of these two filter areas and how to master their interaction.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Using the "Changes Since" Filter for Better Salesforce Pipeline Inspection</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/salesforce-pipeline-episode-2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/salesforce-pipeline-episode-2/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ever found yourself staring at your Salesforce Pipeline Inspection dashboard, scratching your head? You know a deal moved, but it’s not showing up where you expect it to. Or perhaps it appears under “This Week” but vanishes when you select “2 Weeks Ago”?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that sounds familiar, you’re not alone. Pipeline Inspection is a powerful tool for sales leaders and reps, offering dynamic insights into pipeline health. But its “Changes Since” filter, particularly how it calculates “Moved In” and “Moved Out” opportunities, can sometimes feel like a magic trick. Today, we’re pulling back the curtain on that magic, using a real-world scenario to explain exactly what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>