<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Saas on Pavan Chavali</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/tags/saas/</link><description>Recent content in Saas on Pavan Chavali</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pchavali09.github.io/tags/saas/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Episode 2 — “MCP vs MuleSoft: Friends, Not Foes”</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/episode-2-mcp-vs-mulesoft/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/episode-2-mcp-vs-mulesoft/</guid><description>
&lt;img src="https://pchavali09.github.io/1HAaxry-sRt6_ahsalOB3BQ.png" alt="MCP and Mulesoft working intelligently" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve read &lt;a href="https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/episode1-apis-ai-mcp/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Episode 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, you probably remember how we opened the door to this new world of &lt;strong&gt;AI MCP (Model Context Protocol)&lt;/strong&gt; — the idea that systems could start reasoning, not just integrating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It felt exciting, futuristic… maybe &lt;em&gt;too good to be true&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
And honestly, that’s what I’ve been thinking about ever since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because like most of you who’ve lived through long integration nights, broken APIs, and “mysterious” data mismatches — I’ve learned that &lt;em&gt;every shiny new thing&lt;/em&gt; comes with its own set of “gotchas.”&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Platform Renaissance: Why the Future of Enterprise SaaS Is Composable</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/platform-renaissance/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/platform-renaissance/</guid><description>
&lt;img src="https://pchavali09.github.io/19rA7cZugEHvJ-Bk0o17w8Q.png" alt="A digital cloud with composable platform" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For nearly two decades, the enterprise IT playbook has been clear and consistent. In the “Build vs. Buy” debate, the answer overwhelmingly leaned toward &lt;strong&gt;Buy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We adopted Salesforce, Workday, ServiceNow, and other SaaS platforms because they were secure, scalable, and significantly cheaper and faster than building enterprise systems from scratch. The costs, maintenance, and complexity of custom systems made SaaS the pragmatic choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a shift is underway. Enterprises are beginning to ask a deeper question:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Episode 1: From APIs to AI MCP — The Next Chapter of Enterprise Integrations</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/episode-1-from-apis-to-ai-mcp/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/episode-1-from-apis-to-ai-mcp/</guid><description>
&lt;img src="https://pchavali09.github.io/1WEsmOlXSG8A13qWPieHztQ.jpeg" alt="Intelligent Integrations" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever spent late nights debugging APIs, juggling integration flows, or wondering why your “connected systems” don’t actually &lt;em&gt;talk&lt;/em&gt; to each other — this one’s for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This 4-part series explores how enterprise integrations are evolving from traditional APIs and middleware to something smarter — &lt;strong&gt;AI MCP (Model Context Protocol)&lt;/strong&gt; — a new way for systems to communicate &lt;em&gt;intelligently&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(In this first episode, we’ll explore what MCP is, why it matters, and how it changes the way we think about integration.)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Using the "Changes Since" Filter for Better Salesforce Pipeline Inspection</title><link>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/salesforce-pipeline-episode-2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pchavali09.github.io/posts/salesforce-pipeline-episode-2/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;Ever found yourself staring at your Salesforce Pipeline Inspection dashboard, scratching your head? You know a deal moved, but it’s not showing up where you expect it to. Or perhaps it appears under “This Week” but vanishes when you select “2 Weeks Ago”?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that sounds familiar, you’re not alone. Pipeline Inspection is a powerful tool for sales leaders and reps, offering dynamic insights into pipeline health. But its “Changes Since” filter, particularly how it calculates “Moved In” and “Moved Out” opportunities, can sometimes feel like a magic trick. Today, we’re pulling back the curtain on that magic, using a real-world scenario to explain exactly what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>